Guide to the Libby & Edward Marvins Collection, 1940-2018 MS 782
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Libby and Edward Marvins Papers
1912-2018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Marvins, Libby
MS 782
1 Linear Feet 1 Box
This collection contains documents and memorabilia donated by Libby and Edward Marvins related to their time as congregants at Emanu El as well as an oral history conducted with Libby Marvins by staff with the Houston Jewish History Archive in 2018. The materials (including photos, newsprint, correspondence, and other unique items) offer insight into the events and organizations of the Houston Jewish community in the latter half of the 20th century.
Biographical / Historical
Edward "Buz" Zelman Marvins is the son of well-known photographers and philanthropists Sonia and Kaye Marvins, owners of Kaye Marvins Photography in Houston. Edward's wife, Libby Marvins is the Recording Secretary for the National Council of Jewish Women and served on the 2018-2021 Board of the Sisterhood group at Congregation Emanu El. Both Edward and Libby have strong ties to congregation Emanu El, and spend much of their time volunteering in the Houston community.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains newsprint, photographs, documents such as membership lists and pamphlets, and groups of memorabilia such as t-shirts and matchboxes as well as unique items — a matzah cover, a dedicated gavel, and a ceramic planter in the shape of a shoe, as well as an oral history conducted with Libby Marvins by staff with the Houston Jewish History Archive in 2018. The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1940 to 2018. The collection would be a useful resource for researchers interested in local institutions and events, especially congregation Emanu El and its affiliated youth organizations, such as B'nai B'rith Women and Boy Scouts. With its brightly-colored T-shirts and unique memorabilia items, the collection would be ideal for exhibition. Though named for Libby and Edward Marvins, the materials (with the exception of the matzah cover, a family heirloom, and the dedicated gavel) are more relevant to a study of the Jewish community in Houston than a specific study of the Marvins family.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged into two series as follows:
Series I: Photographs, Documents, and Ephemera; Series II: Memorabilia Series III: Oral History
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Libby and Edward Marvins donated the materials in April of 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc.; Religion
Document Types
photographs; letters (correspondence); membership lists; memorabilia; T-shirts; Matchbooks; oral histories (document genres)
Subjects (Persons)
Marvins, Edward
- Series I: Photos, Documents, and Ephemera
  - Boy Scouts Troop 190, Congregation Emanu El, 1950s, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B'nai Brith Lodge #434 Membership Lists, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congregation Emanu El, c. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B'nai B'rith Youth Organization - AZA, c. 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - San Jacinto High School programs, 1964; 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1995, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shearith Israel photograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - D'var Torah, Brief essays, The National Federation of Temple Brotherhood, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Sonia and Kaye Marvins Portrait Collection, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Hadassah Story - a 90-year chronology, 1912-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flashdrive containing photos, 16GB, n.d. (Box 1)
- Series II: Memorabilia
  - Beth Jacob matzah cover, c. mid-late 1940s; Belonged to Bertha Feigelson, Libby Marvin's grandmother Harrison. Possibly a sisterhood gift. (Box 1)
  - Gavel "Presented to Presidents Kaye Marvins by the National Federation of Temple Brotherhood", 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Ceramic sculpture of Shoe "I jogged to the finish--UJC", 1986 (Box 1)
  - Hat labeled "Walk for Israel," n.d. (Box 1)
  - Subseries A: T-Shirts, 1991-2007
    - Senior Olympics "Make Your Mark", 1991 (Box 1)
    - Congregation Emanu El Mitzvah Day, 1993-10-31 (Box 1)
    - JCC Maccabi Games, Houston, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Houston Celebrates Israel 50 Jubilee, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Israel Shopping Fair: Houston, Texas, n.d. (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Plaque presented to Arthur Holland for his many years of service as Treasurer of Shearith Israel Congregation, 1995-05-21 (Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Matchboxes, n.d. (Box 1, Box A)
    - Alfred's of Houston (Box 1, Box A)
    - The Doctor's Club (Box 1, Box A)
    - Esther Wolf Inc. (Box 1, Box A)
    - Glenn H. McCarthy's Cork Club (Box 1, Box A)
    - The Houston Club (Box 1, Box A)
    - Maxim's Restaraunt (Lamar and Milam Houston, Texas) (Box 1, Box A)
    - Riverbend Country Club (Box 1, Box A)
    - Sakowitz Houston (Box 1, Box A)
    - Sugar Creek Country Club (Box 1, Box A)
    - The Warwick Club (Houston, Texas) (Box 1, Box A)
    - Westwood Country Club (8888 Country Creek Dr.) (Box 1, Box A)
    - Westwood Country Club (Houston, Texas) (Box 1, Box A)
- Series III: Oral History
  - Libby Marvins oral history interview and transcript, 2018